Herbert C. Hunsaker Papers
Herbert C. Hunsaker Papers
- Doctoral thesis [DT]
  - Interviews [INTV]
    - Interview recordings
      - 1. George Mitchell, Executive Director, Southern Regional Council, Atlanta; 2. L.R. Seibert, Executive Secretary, Board of Regents of the University System of Georgia, Atlanta, GA; Report of Field Services for Southern Regional by William H. Vastine, 10/20/1953 - 11/06/1953; hunsaker_h_031; 8 inch Blue Soundscriber disc (Box 13)
      - Seminar University of Florida Smith Interview 1. Arnett Smith Seminar 2. School of Education Faculty, hunsaker_h_032; missing physical disc (Box 13)
      - Lafayette Geographic Society Reel One, 04/03/1974; hunsaker_h_033; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 37)
      - Lafayette Geographic Society Reel Two, 04/03/1974; hunsaker_h_034; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 37)
    - Transcripts and correspondence (completed)
      - Transcripts, L to S (Box 5)
      - Transcripts, T to Z (Box 5)
    - Transcripts
      - Transcripts, A to D (Box 5)
      - Transcripts, E to K (Box 5)
      - Transcripts, L to R (Box 5)
      - Transcripts, S to Z (Box 6)
    - Transcripts, rough drafts [not sorted], 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcripts, assorted (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, permission requests A to R (not sorted) (Box 6)
  - Seminars [SEM]
    This material is arranged chronologically. For seminars that met over the course of several years, the folder is filed by the initial meeting date.
    - Seminar in Higher Education, 1952-1953; printed materials (Box 6)
    - University Seminar on Higher Education, 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - Institute for Adult Education [IAE], 1941-1954
      - Course related materials, 1952-1955 (Box 7)
      - Report of the Dean, 1950; Publication list; offprints by Jacob Tuckman and Irving Lorge (Box 7)
      - Community Development seminar
        - Course materials, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Questionnaire (Box 7)
        - Evaluations (Box 7)
    - Role of the University and College in Community Development seminar
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Course materials (Box 7)
      - Course notes (Box 8)
      - Planning, notes; reports; memorandum; Dept of Services & Project Conference in Administration (Box 8)
  - Thesis [THS]
    The material in this subseries includes numerous versions of Hunsaker's doctoral thesis and his notes. The folder labels and their contents remain as they were found. Obvious carbon copies have been removed along with blank forms. The series is arranged as found.
    - "A Study of Some of the Practices and Problems Involved in Extending the Resources of Colleges and Universities into their Communities", 1955?; [incomplete draft with editing marks]; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - "The Role of the College and University in Community Development", 1955; [incomplete draft with editing marks] (Box 8)
    - Chapters II and III, draft with editing marks (Box 8)
      See also Chapter II and Chapter III, below.
    - Committee correspondence and comments (Box 8)
    - Project outlines and suggested titles (Box 8)
    - Outlines of project (Box 8)
    - Project statements (Box 8)
    - Material for HCH project, notes and printed materials (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous ["notes"] (Box 9)
    - Chapter I
      - Purposes and procedures (Box 9)
      - HCH Project (Box 9)
    - Chapter II: Changing Role of Higher Education (Box 9)
      See also Chapters II and III, above.
    - Chapter III
      - University in Community (rough draft), 2 folders (Box 9)
      - University and Community interviews (rough) (Box 9)
      - Fund Toward Community Central Education (Box 9)
      - Extending Community and Universities into Community (Box 9)
    - Chapter IV
      - Community Development (draft) (Box 9)
      - Community Development (draft), 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Final (Box 10)
    - Chapter V: Education for Change (Box 10)
    - Chapter VI
      - Next steps (rough) (Box 10)
      - "Statement prepared by .... for Annual National Conf on Higher Education" [Chapter VI] (Box 10)
    - Not sorted (Box 10)
  - Personal Data [PD]
    - Application to Columbia University [PhD]; transcripts; correspondence; memoranda (Box 10)
    - Fund for Adult Education, 1953-1955; fellowship application; correspondence; expenses; printed materials. (Box 10)
- Professional [PROF]
  - Academic Activities and Conferences [ACT]
    This subseries includes materials relating to Hunsaker's activities as an educator and an administrator in institutions of higher education. Material pertaining to Hunsaker's doctoral studies at Columbia University can be found in the series "Doctoral Thesis." Also included here are conference materials dated between 1936 - ca 1955. The material is arranged in a chronological order.
    - Cleveland College
      - Correspondence; reports; minutes, 1951-1955 (Box 10)
      - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Scrapbook of clippings (Oversize 1)
    - Regional Conference on Universities and World Affairs, 1952-1953; conference materials; Universities and World Affairs No's 1-22; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Annual Faculty Conference, 1953 (Box 11)
      See also Pamphlet files.
    - University of Newark, correspondence; clipping (Box 11)
    - Comprehensive Seminar, 1954; minutes (Box 11)
    - Herald Tribune Forum for High Schools, 1954-1957; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Herald Tribune Forum for High Schools, undated; correspondence; statements; biographic data (Box 11)
    - Herald Tribune Forum for High Schools, 1955-1956; clippings (Box 11)
    - National Training Laboratories [NTL]
      - "Report of the Ninth Summer Laboratory Sessions," Bethel Maine; NTL documents, 1955 (Box 11)
      - Staff meeting in Ann Arbor,; New York City Planning meeting materials, 1954; 1955 (Box 12)
      - Printed materials (Box 12)
    - Purdue University
      - Correspondence, reports, George Davis, 1955-1978; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - WBAA Interview materials, 1958; 1961 (Box 12)
      - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Dept of Gerontology
        - Preliminary Report, 1959 (Box 12)
        - Correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports (Box 12)
        - Bartholomew County Retirement Study (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
      - Proposal for the Further Education of Public Officials, Cultural and Civic Leaders, 1960 (Box 14)
      - Southern Regional Education Board, 1960 (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Educators Conference on Employee Relations, 1956; correspondence; proceedings; miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Ann Arbor Leadership Conference, 1960; conference materials (Box 14)
    - Professors of Adult Education Conference, 1960; proceedings (transcript) (Box 14)
    - The Mentors at the University of Georgia, 1974; memorandum; statements by Mentors, miscellaneous, correspondence (Box 14)
    - Photographs (Box 14)
    - Retirement (Box 14)
    - Conference miscellany (Box 14)
    - Miscellany, offprints; reports; speeches (not HCH); documents (Box 14)
    - Not sorted (Box 14)
  - Speeches and publications [S&P]
    These folders include printed materials, notes, drafts, and corrected typescript copies of speeches. Folder labels are Hunsaker's.
    - Speech materials, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Materials for Paper and Speech for International Conf on University Adult Education, 1960 (Box 15)
    - HCH Writings and Speeches (Box 15)
    - H. C. Hunsaker Speeches, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - H. C. Hunsaker Speeches (cont.) (Box 16)
    - School Executive, correspondence; manuscript; printed materials (Box 16)
    - Articles (offprints) (Box 16)
  - Studies [STD]
    This subseries includes mostly community analysis projects. There are a good number of reports scattered through the Hunsaker collection. Most can found under their sponsoring organization.
    - New York State, University Community Cooperation Project, 1952-1954
      - Reports and proposals; minutes; correspondence; notes; pamphlets; offprints (Box 16)
      - Printed reports (Box 16)
      - Printed materials; clippings; offprints (Box 16)
    - Port Angeles, Washington, Community Study, 1954 (Box 16)
    - Community Education Project of San Bernardino Valley College, 1953; memos; class materials; reports; miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Castle Rock Community Study, Washington, 1954; printed materials, clippings; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Dayton Council on World Affairs, 1953 (Box 17)
  - USAID [USAID], 1961-1969
    - Administrative
      - Correspondence and employment records (Box 17)
      - Rural Development Research Project Seminar; reports (Box 17)
    - Turkey
      - "Fotos [black and white photographic prints] of participants and students in literacy classes" (Box 17)
      - USAID publications (Box 17)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 17)
    - Afghanistan (Box 17)
    - Afghanistan (cont.) (Box 18)
  - UNESCO, 1965
    - Pakistan
      - Engineering education project (Box 18)
      - Correspondence; reports; proposals (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous papers (Box 18)
  - World Education [WED], 1969-1972
    - Administrative
      - USAID contracts, 1969-1972 (Box 18)
      - Annuals reports, 1971; 1972,; 1976 (Box 18)
      - Eevaluation report, 1973 (Box 18)
      - World Education reports, 1972-1979 (Box 18)
      - Promotional (Box 18)
    - Publications
      - The Month in Review, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
      - World Education, 1970-1972 (Box 19)
      - World Education Issues, 1972-1974 (Box 19)
      - World Education Reports, 1972-1979 (Box 19)
    - Literacy Projects, 1969-1972; general reports (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous, notes and documents (Box 19)
    - Afghanistan
      - Correspondence and reports, 1971-1972 (Box 19)
      - Orientation publications and reports (Box 19)
      - Project report, 1971 (Box 19)
      - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Bangladesh, 1972; project proposal (Box 19)
    - India (Literacy House)
      - USAID / India Literacy Board agreements, 1971-1972 (Box 19)
      - Literacy House Work Plan and Budget [three versions], 1971 (Box 19)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1971; includes all correspondence to and from HCH written while under contract to World Education, also "cc" copies of third party letters; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1981; undated; includes all correspondence to and from HCH written while under contract to World Education, also "cc" copies of third party letters; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Correspondence, Welthy Fisher (Box 20)
      - Correspondence, not sorted (Box 20)
      - Reports
        - HCH; by others, 1971-1972; reports cover, to varying degrees, all the countries listed under World Education (Box 20)
        - HCH: India Literacy Board Orqanizational Study, 1971 (Box 20)
      - Workshop and publicity on functional literacy and family life planning education, 1972 (Box 20)
      - Photograph album (from people at Literacy House, India), 1969 (Box 20)
      - Photographs (B&W) of participants at the XXI Writers Workshop, 1970 (Box 20)
      - Photograph (B&W) of participants at the XXI Writers Workshop [oversize], 1970 (Oversize 1)
      - Travel itinerary, 1970 (Box 20)
      - Project proposals, travel notes; incomplete letters and reports (Box 20)
    - Iran
      - Correspondence; reports (Box 20)
      - Work-Oriented Adult Literacy Pilot Project in Iran: Principles, Methods and Techniques for Elaboration of Functional Literacy Programmes (Models and Charts), II [Provisional edition, oversized], undated (Box 21)
      - Reports (UNESCO), ca. 1972 (Box 21)
    - Philippines, report and miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Thailand, reports (Box 21)
    - Turkey, 1970-1972
      - Proposals; reports; memoranda (Box 21)
      - Final report (Box 21)
      - Interview summary with five teachers (Box 21)
      - Teaching aids (Box 21)
      - Annual report, 1971 (Box 21)
- Correspondence [CORR]
  Hunsaker kept a set of "A" to "Z" folders for correspondence and memoranda. The contents of these range form personal to professional. They have been kept intact as listed below. There were also a number of files with correspondence and printed matter that fall under the general heading of professional. They too are listed here.
  - Alley, Rewi, 1979-1980s (Box 21)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1953 (Box 21)
  - Bentley, Harold, 1961-1962 (Box 21)
  - Ciarlillo, Marjorie, 1978-1980 (Box 21)
  - Earp, J.B (Jay Public School), 1940 (Box 21)
  - Sheats, Paul, 1953 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 21)
- Professional Organizations [PROR]
  - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) (Box 22)
  - Adult Education Association (AEA), 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Adult Education Association -- China Tour Committee, 1977-1981 (Box 22)
  - Association for Adult Education of New Jersey (AAENJ) (Box 22)
  - Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) (Box 22)
  - Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) (Box 22)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), International Associates Committee
    - Meeting agenda; minutes; memorandums; membership data (Box 22)
    - Applicants profiles; general administrative documents; correspondence (Box 22)
  - College English Association (CEA) (Box 22)
  - Continuing Education Council (CEC), 1977; correspondence and evaluation documents of M.L. Jones & Associates, Bay Village, Manuscript copy of HCH report, Sept 1977 (Box 22)
  - East-West Communication Institute, 1972; 1974; workshop proposal, 1972; Interim Report on International Conf on Integrated Communication for Rural Development, 1974; newsletter (Box 22)
  - International Council for Adult Education (ICAE)
    - Correspondence (Box 22)
    - Reports (Box 23)
  - National Committee on United States-China Relations, 1974; 1978-1980; correspondence; memorandum; itinerary; publicity; reports; "briefing packet"; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - National University Extension Assoc (NUEA), 1953-1954; annual conference (Box 23)
  - US-China Peoples Friendship Association (US-CPFA)
    - Correspondence (Box 23)
    - Events (Box 23)
    - Handbook for Local Tour Coordinators, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Not sorted, professional-related (Box 23)
- Middle East and China tours
  Hunsaker organized and led a series of tours to the Middle East and China between 1976 and 1984 [1985?]. The tours were sponsored by the AEA. This series is divided by tour.
  - Middle East Tour, 1976; correspondence; orientation materials; administrative documents; publicity; miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - China Tour, 1978
    - Correspondence and memoranda (Box 23)
    - Autobiographical statements by tour participants (Box 23)
    - Orientation materials (Box 23)
    - "China Report", draft and correspondence (Box 24)
    - "Life Long Learning in China," by tour participants (Box 24)
    - Trip evaluations (Box 24)
    - Miscellany (Box 24)
  - China and Far East Study Tour [this trip was canceled], 1979; correspondence; publicity
  - The People's Republic of China Tour, 1980
    - Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Applications and tour evaluations (Box 24)
    - Administrative materials; publicity (Box 24)
    - Manuscript report about trip by participants (Box 24)
    - Miscellany (Box 25)
  - Oriental Adventure, 1982; correspondence; administrative documents; publicity and notes (Box 25)
  - AAACE - Study Tour, 1984; correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Not sorted (Box 25)
- Personal
  This series includes correspondence to and from Herbert and Marion Hunsaker and their children. The correspondence is arranged in chronological order with both incoming and out-going letters filed together.
  - Biographical (Box 25)
  - Certificates [oversized] (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings (Box 25)
  - Clippings, Marion Hunsaker (Box 25)
  - College paper on China, 1920; handwritten with photographs (Box 25)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1939-1959 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1975; 1977-1982,; undated; includes occasional clipping or photograph (Box 26)
  - Council for Student Travel,1957, correspondence; memorandum; reports; publicity (Box 26)
  - Field, Hermann and Kate, 1949-1954; summary of Field case; correspondence; legal documents; clippings (Box 26)
    Items relating to the disappearance of Hermann Field, his brother and brother's wife and child while on a trip to Russia. The Hunsakers were friends of the Fields and HCH was absentee executor of HF's estate. Hermann Field was returned to freedom after six years in jail in Communist Poland.
  - Genealogy (Box 26)
  - Jobs, correspondence [MISSING 8/7/17], 1953-1955
  - Lake Erie College, 1954; 1971-1976; correspondence, 1954; 1971-74; board minutes, 1971-76; report; commencement address, 1973; clippings (Box 27)
  - Legal papers (Box 27)
  - Photographs (Box 27)
  - Rotary Foundation (Box 27)
  - Travel (Box 27)
  - White Salmon (Washington), centennial celebration; clippings (Box 27)
  - Not sorted (Box 27)
- Pamphlet files
  The pamphlets found in the Hunsaker collection were either located in his "Research Material / Field Trip" folders or in separate boxes. All items found in his Research files remain in these folders. The loose pamphlets, series and reports, and offprints have been kept with the collection and are arranged as follows. Periodicals, newsletters and series are arranged alphabetically by title. Subjects headings are listed below. Numbers identify folders.
  - Periodicals
    - Adult Education, 1953; 1957-1961; 19 issues, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Adult Education, 1961-1962; 5 issues, 1 folder (Box 28)
    - Adult Education Bulletin, 1947; 3 issues (Box 28)
    - Bulletin [of the World Association for Adult Education], 1942-1945; 7 issues (Box 28)
    - Community Councils in Action, 1940-1941; 4 issues (Box 28)
    - Community Development Bulletin, 1956; 1 issue (Box 28)
    - Food for Thought, 1940-1941; 3 issues (Box 28)
    - H-J (Box 28)
      The Highway [Workers' Educational Association], 1953, 1 issue
      International Conciliation, 1942-1943, 3 issues
      International Journal of Adult and Youth Education, 1961, 1 issue
      Journal of Educational Sociology, 1952, 1 issue
    - Notes and Essays on Education for Adults, no 6, 8, 9, 13, 17-22, 25-30; 16 issues (Box 28)
    - R-U (Box 29)
      Review of Educational Research, 1959, 1 issue
      Rewley House Papers, 1953-1957, 1960-1961, 5 issues
      Tutors' Bulletin of Adult Education, 1953, 1 issue
      University of the State of New York Bulletin, 1948, 1 issue
  - Newsletters (Box 29)
  - Series
    - American Community Project at New York University, no 1-8, leader's guide, participant's manual (Box 29)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA), 1959; 4 issues (Box 29)
    - Higher Education for American Democracy, vol. 1-5 (Box 29)
    - Learning for Living (Canadian Association for Adult Education) (Box 29)
    - National Old People's Welfare Council, 1958-1961; annual report, progress report (Box 29)
    - Public Affairs Pamphlet, no's 194, 209 (Box 29)
  - Professional associations
    - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA/USA) (Box 29)
    - American Association for Adult Education (Box 29)
    - American Association of University Women (AAUW) (Box 30)
    - Associates in Negro Folk Education (Box 30)
    - Board of Control for Southern Regional Education (Box 30)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA), 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Fund for Adult Education (FAE) (Box 30)
    - Fund for the Advancement of Education (Box 30)
    - National Education Association of the United States; American Association of School Administrators (Box 30)
    - National University Extension Association (NUEA) (Box 30)
    - New York Adult Education Council (Box 30)
    - Residential Colleges Committee (Box 30)
    - Workers' Educational Association (Box 30)
  - UNESCO, 4 folders (Box 30)
  - Universities
    - City College of the City of New York (Box 30)
    - Columbia University (Box 30)
    - Indiana University (Box 30)
    - New York University (Box 30)
    - Ruskin College (Box 30)
    - University of Georgia (Box 30)
    - University of Georgia (Box 31)
    - University of Pittsburgh (Box 31)
  - Subjects
    - Adult Education, general (Box 32)
    - Community Dynamics Experiment (Box 32)
    - Community studies, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - Community studies (cont.) (Box 33)
    - Conference proceeding and schedules (Box 33)
      City Literary Institute, London, 1948
      International Conference on Comparative Education, Chiemsee, Germany, 1949
      Leadership Conference, CSLEA, Chicaco, 1949
      National Adult Education Conference, Portland, Oregon, 1978
      Southwest Regional Conference on Adult Education, Austin, Texas, 1940
      University of California All-University Faculty, Davis, California, 1947, 1949-1954
    - Discussion group methods (Box 33)
    - Exhibition catalogs (Box 33)
    - Government publications, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - International concerns, 4 folders (Box 33)
    - Music, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Offprints (Box 35)
    - Public school (Box 35)
    - Papers and reports, general, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Papers and reports, general, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - Race relations (Box 36)
    - School - community relations, 3 folders (Box 36)
    - Television and radio (Box 36)
    - The university (Box 37)
  - Dunn, Halbert L. Your World and Mine: Essays on Human Relations. NY: Exposition Pr,., 1956; signed and inscribed to Hunsaker by author; photocopy of cover and inscription page only (Box 37)
    Book sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
  - Dyer, John. Ivory Towers in the Market Places: The Evening College in American Education. NY: Bobbs-Merrill., 1956; signed and inscribed to Hunsaker by author; photocopy of cover and inscription page only (Box 37)
  - McKee, Elmore M. The People Act: Stories of How Americans Are Coming Together to Deal With Their Community Problems. NY: Harper and Brothers., 1955; signed and inscribed to Hunsaker by author; photocopy of cover and inscription page only (Box 37)